<?xml version="1.0"?>
<courseleaf>

<title>Communication, Computation, and Statistics</title>


<text>
<![CDATA[  
<h2>Overview</h2>
<p>The Designated Emphasis (DE) in Communication, Computation, and Statistics provides an academic structure for an interdisciplinary exchange of ideas. Many of the most significant developments in modern information technology — including communication and data networks; multimedia information processing; and large-scale, distributed data analysis in science, engineering, and commerce — are no longer the province of a single academic field, but draw on ideas from diverse sources in computer science, electrical engineering, and statistics. The DE in Communication, Computation, and Statistics enables specialized, multidisciplinary training, and research opportunities in various emerging areas of information technology. Admitted students not only participate in a cutting-edge program and receive explicit recognition of specialization in the Designated Emphasis but are also well positioned to compete for the most desirable jobs in information technology, both in academia and in industry.</p>
<h3>Graduate Program</h3>
<p><a href="/2019-20/graduate/degree-programs/communication-computation-statistics/">Communication, Computation, and Statistics</a>: Designated Emphasis (DE)</p>
  
]]>
</text>
<faculty>
<![CDATA[
<h2>Faculty and Instructors</h2><h4>Faculty</h4><p class="facitem"><strong>Pieter Abbeel, <i>Associate Professor</i>. </strong>Artificial Intelligence (AI), Control, Intelligent Systems, and Robotics (CIR), Machine Learning.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/faculty/pieter-abbeel"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>David Aldous, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Mathematical probability, applied probability, analysis of algorithms, phylogenetic trees, complex networks, random networks, entropy, spatial networks.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14271"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Venkat Anantharam, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Communications & Networking (COMNET), Artificial Intelligence (AI), Control, Intelligent Systems, and Robotics (CIR), Security (SEC), Signal Processing (SP).<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/faculty/venkat-anantharam"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Peter L. Bartlett, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Statistics, machine learning, statistical learning theory, adaptive control.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14413"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Alexandre M. Bayen, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Transportation, modelling and control of distributed parameters systems, large scale infrastructure systems, water distribution.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14130"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>John Canny, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Computer science, activity-based computing, livenotes, mechatronic devices, flexonics.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14606"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Laurent El Ghaoui, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Decision-making under uncertainty, convex optimization, robust solutions, semidefinite programming, exhaustive simulation.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/15019"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Noureddine El Karoui, <i>Associate Professor</i>. </strong>Applied statistics, theory and applications of random matrices, large dimensional covariance estimation and properties of covariance matrices, connections with mathematical finance.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/15021"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Adityanand Guntuboyina, <i>Assistant Professor</i>. </strong>Nonparametric and high-dimensional statistics, shape constrained statistical estimation, empirical processes, statistical information theory.</p><p class="facitem"><strong>Michael I. Jordan, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Computer science, artificial intelligence, bioinformatics, statistics, machine learning, electrical engineering, applied statistics, optimization.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/13970"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Daniel Klein, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Artificial Intelligence (AI), Natural Language Processing, Computational Linguistics, Machine Learning.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/faculty/daniel-klein"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Robert C. Leachman, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Logistics, manufacturing, semiconductors, scheduling, supply chain systems, dynamic production models, production planning and scheduling.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14996"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Edward A. Lee, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Embedded Software, Real-Time Systems, Cyber-Physical Systems, Concurrency, Design, Modeling and Analysis (DMA), Programming Systems (PS),Signal Processing (SP).<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/faculty/edward-lee"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Jitendra Malik, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Artificial Intelligence (AI), Biosystems & Computational Biology (BIO), Control, Intelligent Systems, and Robotics (CIR), Graphics (GR), Human-Computer Interaction (HCI), Signal Processing (SP),.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/faculty/jitendra-malik"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Kannan Ramchandran, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Communications & Networking (COMNET), Signal Processing (SP), Control, Intelligent Systems, and Robotics (CIR).<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/faculty/kannan-ramchandran"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Benjamin Recht, <i>Associate Professor</i>. </strong>Control, Intelligent Systems, and Robotics (CIR), Signal Processing (SP), Machine Learning (ML), Optimization (OPT).</p><p class="facitem"><strong>Stuart Russell, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Artificial intelligence, computational biology, algorithms, machine learning, real-time decision-making, probabilistic reasoning.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/faculty/stuart-j-russell"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Anant Sahai, <i>Associate Professor</i>. </strong>Communications & Networking (COMNET), Information Theory, Cognitive Radio and Spectrum Sharing, Control, Intelligent Systems, and Robotics (CIR), Distributed and Networked Control, Signal Processing (SP), Theory (THY), Information Theory.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/faculty/anant-sahai"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>S. Shankar Sastry, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Computer science, robotics, arial robots, cybersecurity, cyber defense, homeland defense, nonholonomic systems, control of hybrid systems, sensor networks, interactive visualization, robotic telesurgery, rapid prototyping.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/13862"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Alistair Sinclair, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Theory (THY), Randomized algorithms, applied probability, statistical physics.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/faculty/alistair-sinclair"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Claire Tomlin, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Control, Intelligent Systems, and Robotics (CIR), Biosystems & Computational Biology (BIO), Control theory, hybrid and embedded systems, biological cell networks.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/faculty/claire-tomlin"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Martin Wainwright, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Statistical machine learning, High-dimensional statistics, information theory, Optimization and algorithmss .<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/15701"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Bin Yu, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Neuroscience, remote sensing, networks, statistical machine learning, high-dimensional inference, massive data problems, document summarization .<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14282"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Avideh Zakhor, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Signal Processing (SP), Artificial Intelligence (AI), Control, Intelligent Systems, and Robotics (CIR), Graphics (GR).<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/faculty/avideh-zakhor"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><h4>Emeritus Faculty</h4><p class="facitem"><strong>Peter J. Bickel, <i>Professor Emeritus</i>. </strong>Statistics, machine learning, semiparametric models, asymptotic theory, hidden Markov models, applications to molecular biology.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/13924"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Jerome A. Feldman, <i>Professor Emeritus</i>. </strong>Artificial Intelligence (AI), Biosystems & Computational Biology (BIO), Security (SEC), cognitive science.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/faculty/jerome-feldman"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Nelson Morgan, <i>Professor Emeritus</i>. </strong>Signal Processing (SP).</p><p class="facitem"><strong>John A. Rice, <i>Professor Emeritus</i>. </strong>Transportation, astronomy, statistics, functional data analysis, time series analysis.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/13988"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Pravin Varaiya, <i>Professor Emeritus</i>. </strong>Communications & Networking (COMNET), Control, Intelligent Systems, and Robotics (CIR), Energy (ENE), Control, Networks, Power systems, Transportation.</p>]]>
</faculty>
</courseleaf>

