<?xml version="1.0"?>
<courseleaf>

<title>Latin American Studies</title>


<text>
<![CDATA[  

  
]]>
</text>
<abouttheprogramtext>
<![CDATA[
<h3><span>Bachelor of Arts (BA)</span></h3>
<p><strong>Note: The Latin American Studies Major has been retired and folded into Global Studies.  We are no longer accepting Latin American Studies declarations.  Please visit the</strong> <strong><a href="http://globalstudies.berkeley.edu/">Global Studies website</a></strong> <strong>or the</strong> <strong><a href="/2019-20/undergraduate/degree-programs/global-studies/">Global Studies</a></strong> p<strong>age on the Berkeley Academic Guide for more information.  </strong></p>
<p>The major in Latin American Studies (LAS) is designed to provide a balanced curriculum in the history, culture, and society of Latin America for students wishing to receive a broader perspective than is usually available through a department major. From the rich variety of offerings within and across departments, there is a wide range of possibilities to suit the interests of students. The program may be of particular interest to students who:</p>
<ul>
	<li>Plan to enter business, government, or international agency service.</li>
	<li>Wish to teach social science or language.</li>
	<li>Are preparing for graduate and professional schools.</li>
</ul>
<p>There is a wide range of courses from numerous departments to suit the interests of LAS majors. Students must gain intermediate-level proficiency in their chosen language — equivalent to four college-level semesters—either Spanish or Portuguese. In addition, students pursue a multidisciplinary course of study that includes the history and literature of the region. To assist in organizing a plan of study, students are aided by participating faculty members from several departments and programs, the faculty chair of the major, major advisers in the International and Area Studies Office, and teaching associates working in the program.</p>
<h3>Declaring the Major</h3>
<p>Applications are accepted during the fall and spring semesters from the third week of instruction until the last day of instruction (not the last day of finals). Applications are accepted during the summer from the last week in May until the beginning of the fall semester (not the beginning of classes).</p>
<p>To declare, students must satisfy the following:</p>
<ol>
	<li>Have completed <span class="sc_courseinline">LATAMST 10</span> (offered in fall semester only) with a grade of C or better (C- does not satisfy this requirement); Note: LAS 10 maybe be repeated <em>only once</em> to achieve a grade of C or better. There is no equivalent for LAS 10 from California community colleges.</li>
	<li>Transfer students (only) may declare the major while enrolled in LAS 10. However, if a grade of C or better is not achieved, transfer students must repeat the course. A grade of C or better must be achieved on the second attempt.</li>
	<li>Have a major and cumulative GPA of 2.0 or higher.</li>
	<li>Not be in their final semester of undergraduate work.</li>
	<li class="Default">Have attended a Major Declaration Workshop (check the IAS website at  <a href="http://iastp.berkeley.edu/">http://iastp.berkeley.edu/</a> or the posted calendar in 101 Stephens Hall for dates).</li>
</ol>
<p>Additionally, students are encouraged—but not required—to complete two semesters of Spanish or Portuguese or the equivalent before applying to the major.</p>
<p>To be declared, students must do three things:</p>
<ol>
	<li>Meet with an LAS adviser to review the application materials.</li>
	<li>After having met with an LAS adviser, it is highly recommended that intended LAS majors take all application materials to the LAS Chair, Professor Estelle Tarica at 5214 in Dwinelle Hall for review.</li>
	<li>Submit all the application materials to an LAS Adviser at the IAS Office in 101 Stephens Hall.</li>
</ol>
<p>A completed LAS application includes: an Application Form and Program Worksheet, current Bearfacts unofficial transcript with the course that will be counted for the major highlighted, official transcripts from all other colleges attended with coursework the student intends to count toward the major, “Petition to Declare a Major&quot; form signed by the student, Personal Statement—a typed, double-spaced, one-page essay describing the student’s interest in LAS. In the statement, students should describe their interest in the major, their career aspirations, any plans for a higher degree, future goals, and anything else relevant to studying Latin American Studies.</p>
<h3>Honors Program</h3>
<p>To be eligible for honors, students must have senior standing and a grade point average (GPA) of 3.6 in the major and 3.5 in all work completed at UC Berkeley. Completing the honors program includes a year-long course sequence (<span class="sc_courseinline">IAS H102</span> in the fall and <span class="sc_courseinline">LATAMST H195</span> in the spring) in which students learn how to formulate a hypothesis, conduct supporting research, and complete a thesis paper of approximately 75 pages or longer.</p>
<h3 class="Default">Faculty Thesis Adviser</h3>
<p class="Default">Honors students must also enlist a faculty thesis adviser with whom they will meet throughout the year to discuss the content of their thesis. Potential honors students are strongly encouraged to start early to find a faculty thesis adviser, preferably during the spring semester of their junior year, but no later than the end of September of their senior year. Most faculty will only advise on a thesis topic that is within their subject area, and many prefer to work with students they know or have taught. The completed thesis is read and evaluated by both the seminar instructor and the faculty thesis adviser.</p>
<p class="Default">Three copies of the honors thesis must be provided by the student: one for the seminar instructor, one for the student’s faculty thesis adviser, and one for reference at the IAS Office. Sample honors thesis titles include:</p>
<ul>
	<li>Guatemalan Coffee Farmers and the Fair Trade Movement.</li>
	<li>The Brazilian Landless Rural Workers’ Movement (MST): Deconstructing Nonviolence Theory.</li>
	<li>Andean Fiestas: A Mirror of Cajatambo’s Reality from 1900 to 2007.</li>
</ul>
<p class="Default"><strong>Please note:</strong> There is no guarantee that students who complete the honors sequence will graduate with honors. Honors recommendations are made after graduation and are based on a number of factors including (but not limited to) major GPA, overall GPA, grade received in H195, and thesis reader recommendations. </p>
<h3>Minor Program</h3>
<p>There is no minor program in Latin American Studies. LAS majors are encouraged to enhance their undergraduate degree by completing minors in other disciplines. No more than one upper division course may be used to satisfy requirements in both a major and minor.</p>
<div> </div>
]]>
</abouttheprogramtext>
<majorrequirementstext>
<![CDATA[
<p>In addition to the University, campus, and college requirements, listed on the College Requirements tab, students must fulfill the below requirements specific to their major program.</p>
<h3>Repeat Rule</h3>
<p>Students who earn a grade of F, D-, D, D+ or NP may repeat the course only once. Regardless of the grade the student receives for their second attempt (including F, D-, D or D+), the student may <strong>not</strong> repeat the course a third time.</p>
<h3>General Guidelines</h3>
<ol>
	<li class="Default">No more than three upper division courses taken outside of the College of Letters &amp; Science, including courses taken at other universities, EAP, study abroad and other colleges on the UC Berkeley campus, may count towards major requirements.</li>
	<li class="Default">No more than four upper division courses may be taken from the same department.</li>
	<li class="Default">Courses cannot be double-counted within the major (for example, students may not use one course to fulfill both a history requirement and an electives requirement).</li>
	<li class="Default">All courses in the major must be taken for a letter grade. The one exception is foreign language: only the fourth semester level class must be taken for a letter grade. The first, second, and third semester language classes may be taken Pass/Not Pass. </li>
	<li>No more than one upper division course may be used to simultaneously fulfill requirements for a student's major and minor programs, with the exception of minors offered outside of the College of Letters &amp; Science.</li>
	<li>A minimum grade point average (GPA) of 2.0 must be maintained in both upper and lower division courses used to fulfill the major requirements.</li>
	<li class="Default">Online courses are not accepted in the major.</li>
</ol>
<p>For information regarding residence requirements and unit requirements, please see the College Requirements tab.</p>
<h3>Summary of Major Requirements</h3>
<table class="sc_courselist" width="100%">
<caption class="hidden noscript">Course List</caption>
<colgroup><col class="codecol"/><col class="titlecol"/><col align="char" char="." class="hourscol"/></colgroup><thead><tr class="hidden noscript"><th scope="col">Code</th><th scope="col">Title</th><th scope="col" class="hourscol">Units</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr class="even firstrow"><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment">Lower Division Requirements: Two courses</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment">Primary Language Requirement, Spanish or Portuguese: Intermediate level of proficiency</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment">Secondary Language Requirement, Spanish or Portuguese: Optional</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd lastrow"><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment">Upper Division Requirements: Nine courses, minimum of 30 units</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<h3>Lower Division Requirements</h3>
<table class="sc_courselist" width="100%">
<caption class="hidden noscript">Course List</caption>
<colgroup><col class="codecol"/><col class="titlecol"/><col align="char" char="." class="hourscol"/></colgroup><thead><tr class="hidden noscript"><th scope="col">Code</th><th scope="col">Title</th><th scope="col" class="hourscol">Units</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr class="even firstrow"><td class="codecol">LATAMST 10</td><td>Introduction to Latin American Studies <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd lastrow"><td class="codecol">HISTORY 8A</td><td>Latin American History: Becoming Latin America, 1492 to 1824</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="orclass odd lastrow"><td class="codecol orclass">or HISTORY 8B</td><td colspan="2"> Latin American History: Modern Latin America</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<table role="presentation" border="0" width="100%" class="sc_footnotes"><tr><td valign="top" class="symcol"><sup>1</sup></td><td class="notecol"><p>This course can only be repeated once.</p></td></tr></table>
<h3>Primary Language Requirement<sup>1</sup></h3>
<p>LAS majors must demonstrate an intermediate level of proficiency in either Spanish or Portuguese equivalent to four college-level semesters.  Language courses taken in high school do not satisfy this requirement. See below for details on how to fulfill the foreign language requirement. For information regarding satisfying this requirement through other means than the courses below (AP credit, Native speakers), please see the <a href="http://iastp.berkeley.edu" target="_blank">program's website</a>.</p>
<table class="sc_courselist" width="100%">
<caption class="hidden noscript">Course List</caption>
<colgroup><col class="codecol"/><col class="titlecol"/><col align="char" char="." class="hourscol"/></colgroup><thead><tr class="hidden noscript"><th scope="col">Code</th><th scope="col">Title</th><th scope="col" class="hourscol">Units</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr class="even firstrow"><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment">Select either the Spanish or Portuguese sequence below, or their equivalent:</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment">Spanish</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">SPANISH 1</div></td><td>Elementary Spanish [5]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">SPANISH 2</div></td><td>Elementary Spanish [5]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">SPANISH 3</div></td><td>Intermediate Spanish [5]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">SPANISH 4</div></td><td>Intermediate Spanish [5]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment">Portugese</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">PORTUG 101A</div></td><td>Course Not Available</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">PORTUG 101B</div></td><td>Course Not Available</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">PORTUG 102</div></td><td>Readings in Portuguese [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even lastrow"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">PORTUG 103</div></td><td>Advanced Grammar and Composition [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<h3>Secondary Language (Optional)</h3>
<p>LAS major are encouraged to pursue a second language, either Spanish or Portuguese. </p>
<table class="sc_courselist" width="100%">
<caption class="hidden noscript">Course List</caption>
<colgroup><col class="codecol"/><col class="titlecol"/><col align="char" char="." class="hourscol"/></colgroup><thead><tr class="hidden noscript"><th scope="col">Code</th><th scope="col">Title</th><th scope="col" class="hourscol">Units</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr class="even firstrow"><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment">Complete one of the following sequences, or their equivalent</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">PORTUG 101A<br/><span style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">&amp; PORTUG 101B</span></div></td><td>Course Not Available<br/><span style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">and Course Not Available</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even lastrow"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">SPANISH 1<br/><span style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">&amp; SPANISH 2</span></div></td><td>Elementary Spanish<br/><span style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">and Elementary Spanish</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="orclass even lastrow"><td class="codecol orclass"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">or SPANISH 6</div></td><td colspan="2"> Course Not Available</td></tr>
<tr class="orclass even lastrow"><td class="codecol orclass"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">or SPANISH 21</div></td><td colspan="2"> Spanish for Bilingual Students, First Course</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<table role="presentation" border="0" width="100%" class="sc_footnotes"><tr><td valign="top" class="symcol"><sup>1</sup></td><td class="notecol"><p>The primary and secondary foreign language requirements may be taken <em>Pass/No Pass</em>, except for the final semester of each sequence; the final semester must be taken for a letter grade.</p></td></tr></table>
<h3>Upper Division Requirements</h3>
<table class="sc_courselist" width="100%">
<caption class="hidden noscript">Course List</caption>
<colgroup><col class="codecol"/><col class="titlecol"/><col align="char" char="." class="hourscol"/></colgroup><thead><tr class="hidden noscript"><th scope="col">Code</th><th scope="col">Title</th><th scope="col" class="hourscol">Units</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr class="even areaheader  firstrow"><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment areaheader ">Latin American Literature and Culture (Two Courses)</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment">Select one of the following sequences, depending on the choice of primary language:</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">SPANISH 104A<br/><span style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">&amp; SPANISH 104B</span></div></td><td>Survey of Spanish American Literature<br/><span style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">and Survey of Spanish American Literature</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">PORTUG 104<br/><span style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">&amp; PORTUG 107B</span></div></td><td>Introduction to Brazilian Literature<br/><span style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">and Course Not Available</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">PORTUG 128<br/><span style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">&amp; PORTUG 107B</span></div></td><td>Twentieth-Century Brazilian Literature<br/><span style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">and Course Not Available</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd areaheader "><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment areaheader ">Latin American History (Two Courses)</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment">Select two courses from the following:</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">HISTORY 100</div></td><td>Course Not Available [4] <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">HISTORY 101</div></td><td>Seminar in Historical Research and Writing for History Majors [5]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">HISTORY 103E</div></td><td>Proseminar: Problems in Interpretation in the Several Fields of History: Latin America [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">HISTORY 140B</div></td><td>Mexico: Modern Mexico [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">HISTORY 141B</div></td><td>Social History of Latin America: Social History of Modern Latin America [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">HISTORY 143</div></td><td>Brazil [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">HISTORY 146</div></td><td>Latin American Women [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">LATAMST 150</div></td><td>Advanced Studies in Latin American Studies [4] <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd areaheader "><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment areaheader ">Methodology (One Course)</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment">Select one course from either the Statistical Methods category or the Research Design category:</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd areaheader "><td colspan="2"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent"><span class="courselistcomment areaheader  commentindent">Statistical Methods</span></div></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">DEMOG 110</div></td><td>Introduction to Population Analysis [3]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">ECON 140</div></td><td>Economic Statistics and Econometrics [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">ECON 141</div></td><td>Econometric Analysis [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">ECON C142</div></td><td>Applied Econometrics and Public Policy [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">IAS C118</div></td><td>Introductory Applied Econometrics [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">IND ENG 162</div></td><td>Linear Programming and Network Flows [3]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">IND ENG 171</div></td><td>Technology Firm Leadership [3]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">POL SCI C131A</div></td><td>Applied Econometrics and Public Policy [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">PSYCH 101</div></td><td>Research and Data Analysis in Psychology [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">PB HLTH 142</div></td><td>Introduction to Probability and Statistics in Biology and Public Health [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">PUB POL C142</div></td><td>Applied Econometrics and Public Policy [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">SOCIOL 106</div></td><td>Quantitative Sociological Methods [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">STAT 131A</div></td><td>Statistical Methods for Data Science [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd areaheader "><td colspan="2"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent"><span class="courselistcomment areaheader  commentindent">Research Design</span></div></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">AFRICAM 101</div></td><td>Research Methods for African American Studies [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">ANTHRO 169B</div></td><td>Research Theory and Methods in Socio-Cultural Anthropology [5]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">ENV DES 100</div></td><td>The City: Theories and Methods in Urban Studies [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">ETH STD 101A</div></td><td>Social Science Methods in Ethnic Studies [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">ETH STD 101B</div></td><td>Humanities Methods in Ethnic Studies [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">ETH STD 195</div></td><td>Selected Issues in Comparative Ethnic Studies Research [4] <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">IAS 102</div></td><td>Scope and Methods of Research in International and Area Studies [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">IAS H102</div></td><td>Scope and Methods of Research in International and Area Studies [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">LGBT 145</div></td><td>Interpreting the Queer Past: Methods and Problems in the History of Sexuality [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">NATAMST 110</div></td><td>Theories and Methods in Native American Studies [4]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol"><div style="margin-left:20px;" class="blockindent">SOCIOL 105</div></td><td>Research Design and Sociological Methods [5]</td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd areaheader "><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment areaheader ">Electives (Four Courses)</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even lastrow"><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment">Select four courses from the list of approved electives (see below), from at least two disciplines other than literature and history</span> <sup>2</sup></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<table role="presentation" border="0" width="100%" class="sc_footnotes"><tr><td valign="top" class="symcol"><sup>1</sup></td><td class="notecol"><p>Course content varies from semester to semester. A faculty adviser's preapproval is required.</p></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" class="symcol"><sup>2</sup></td><td class="notecol"><p>No more than two upper division electives may be taken from the same department.</p></td></tr></table>
<h3>Approved Elective Course List</h3>
<table class="sc_courselist" width="100%">
<caption class="hidden noscript">Course List</caption>
<colgroup><col class="codecol"/><col class="titlecol"/><col align="char" char="." class="hourscol"/></colgroup><thead><tr class="hidden noscript"><th scope="col">Code</th><th scope="col">Title</th><th scope="col" class="hourscol">Units</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr class="even firstrow"><td class="codecol">AFRICAM 112A</td><td>Political and Economic Development in the Third World</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">AFRICAM 112B</td><td>Political and Economic Development in the Third World</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">AFRICAM 131</td><td>Caribbean Societies and Cultures</td><td class="hourscol">3</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">ANTHRO 122C</td><td>Archaeology of the Americas: Archaeology of Central America</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">ANTHRO 122D</td><td>Archaeology of the Americas: World of Ancient Maya</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">ANTHRO 122E</td><td>Archaeology of the Americas: Andean Archaeology: People of the Andes</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">ANTHRO 140</td><td>The Anthropology of Food <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">ANTHRO C147B</td><td>Sexuality, Culture, and Colonialism</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">ANTHRO 179</td><td>Ethnography of the Maya</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">CHICANO 110</td><td>Latina/o Philosophy and Religious Thought</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">CHICANO 143</td><td>Chicano and Latin American Literature</td><td class="hourscol">3</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">CHICANO 150B</td><td>History of the Southwest: Mexican-United States War to Present</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">CHICANO 159</td><td>Mexican Immigration</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">CHICANO C161</td><td>Central American Peoples and Cultures</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">CHICANO 163</td><td>Caribbean Migration to Western Europe and the United States <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">CHICANO 165</td><td>Cuba, the United States and Cuban Americans</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">CHICANO 174</td><td>Chicanos, Law, and Criminal Justice <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">CHICANO 180</td><td>Topics in Chicano Studies <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">3</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">CY PLAN 115</td><td>Urbanization in Developing Countries</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">COM LIT 156</td><td>Fiction and Culture of the Americas</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">DEMOG 145AC</td><td>The American Immigrant Experience</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">DEV STD 150</td><td>Advanced Studies in Development Studies <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">ECON C171</td><td>Development Economics <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">ECON 172</td><td>Case Studies in Economic Development <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">ENVECON C151</td><td>Development Economics</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">ETH STD 159AC</td><td>The Southern Border</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">ETH STD 195</td><td>Selected Issues in Comparative Ethnic Studies Research</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">FRENCH 151A</td><td>Francophone Literature</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">FRENCH 151B</td><td>Francophone Literature</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">GEOG 123</td><td>Postcolonial Geographies <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">GEOG 170</td><td>Special Topics in Geography <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">3</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">GEOG 138</td><td>Global Environmental Politics <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">GEOG C157</td><td>Central American Peoples and Cultures</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">GEOG 159AC</td><td>The Southern Border</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">GWS 102</td><td>Transnational Feminism <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">GWS 103</td><td>Identities Across Difference <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">GWS 129</td><td>Bodies and Boundaries <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">GWS 140</td><td>Feminist Cultural Studies <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">GWS 141</td><td>Interrogating Global Economic &quot;Development&quot; <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">GWS 142</td><td>Women in the Muslim and Arab Worlds</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">GWS 143</td><td>Women, Proverty, and Globalization <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">HISTORY 100</td><td>Course Not Available <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">HISTORY 103E</td><td>Proseminar: Problems in Interpretation in the Several Fields of History: Latin America</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">HISTORY C139B</td><td>The American Immigrant Experience</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">HISTORY 140B</td><td>Mexico: Modern Mexico</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">HISTORY 141B</td><td>Social History of Latin America: Social History of Modern Latin America</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">HISTORY 143</td><td>Brazil</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">HISTORY 146</td><td>Latin American Women</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">LATAMST 150</td><td>Advanced Studies in Latin American Studies</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">LEGALST 190</td><td>Seminar on Topics in Law and Society <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">1-4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">PACS 130</td><td>Cross-Listed Topics <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">1-4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">PACS 135</td><td>Special Topics in Regional Conflict <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">3</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">POLECON 150</td><td>Advanced Study in Political Economy of Industrial Societies <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">POL SCI 139D</td><td>Urban and Sub-national Politics in Developing Countries <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">POL SCI 148A</td><td>Latin American Politics</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">POL SCI 149B</td><td>Special Topics in Area Studies</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">PORTUG 102</td><td>Readings in Portuguese</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">PORTUG 104</td><td>Introduction to Brazilian Literature</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">PORTUG 113</td><td>Brazilian Civilization</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">PORTUG 128</td><td>Twentieth-Century Brazilian Literature</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">PORTUG 135</td><td>Studies in Luso-Brazilian Literature <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">PB HLTH 181</td><td>Poverty and Population <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">3</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">PUB POL 190</td><td>Special Topics in Public Policy <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">1-4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">SOCIOL 111P</td><td>Families, Inequality and Social Policy <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">SOCIOL 124</td><td>Sociology of Poverty <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">SOCIOL 127</td><td>Development and Globalization <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">SOCIOL 130</td><td>Social Inequalities <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">SOCIOL 140</td><td>Politics and Social Change <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">SOCIOL 189</td><td>Selected Topics in Comparative Perspectives <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">SOC WEL 274</td><td>Immigrants and Refugees in the U.S <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">2</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">SPANISH 104A</td><td>Survey of Spanish American Literature</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">SPANISH 104B</td><td>Survey of Spanish American Literature</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">SPANISH 113</td><td>Topics in Latin American Culture</td><td class="hourscol">3</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">SPANISH 135</td><td>Studies in Hispanic Literature <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even lastrow"><td class="codecol">SPANISH C178</td><td>Cultural Studies</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<table role="presentation" border="0" width="100%" class="sc_footnotes"><tr><td valign="top" class="symcol"><sup>1</sup></td><td class="notecol"><p>Course content varies from semester to semester. A faculty adviser's preapproval is required.</p></td></tr></table>
]]>
</majorrequirementstext>
<collegerequirementstext>
<![CDATA[
 <p>Undergraduate students must fulfill the following requirements in addition to those required by their major program.</p> <p>For detailed lists of courses that fulfill college requirements, please review the <a href="/2019-20/undergraduate/colleges-schools/letters-science/">College of Letters &amp; Sciences</a> page in this Guide. For College advising appointments, please visit the <a href="https://ls.berkeley.edu/advising/about-undergraduate-advising-services">L&amp;S Advising</a> Pages. </p> <h3>University of California Requirements</h3> <h5><a href="http://writing.berkeley.edu/node/78"><span id="docs-internal-guid-82322469-d403-b6fc-99fe-5be6e0865dad">Entry Level Writing</span></a></h5> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-82322469-d403-c602-c395-1fb0f53c604b">All students who will enter the University of California as freshmen must demonstrate their command of the English language by fulfilling the Entry Level Writing requirement. Fulfillment of this requirement is also a prerequisite to enrollment in all reading and composition courses at UC Berkeley. </span></p> <h5><a href="/2019-20/undergraduate/colleges-schools/letters-science/american-history-institutions-requirement/"><span id="docs-internal-guid-82322469-d403-ed90-bc30-8e7c7e9092f7">American History and American Institutions</span></a></h5> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-82322469-d403-fe3e-933e-7102e097ef4b">The American History and Institutions requirements are based on the principle that a US resident graduated from an American university, should have an understanding of the history and governmental institutions of the United States.</span></p> <h3><span>Berkeley Campus Requirement</span></h3> <h5><a href="http://americancultures.berkeley.edu/students/courses"><span id="docs-internal-guid-82322469-d404-3abc-dc51-fc563caacff1">American Cultures</span></a></h5> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-82322469-d404-47e1-1ad4-b918d33461cf">All undergraduate students at Cal need to take and pass this course in order to graduate. The requirement offers an exciting intellectual environment centered on the study of race, ethnicity and culture of the United States. AC courses offer students opportunities to be part of research-led, highly accomplished teaching environments, grappling with the complexity of American Culture.</span></p> <h3><span>College of Letters &amp; Science Essential Skills Requirements</span></h3> <h5><a href="/2019-20/undergraduate/colleges-schools/letters-science/quantitative-reasoning-requirement/"><span id="docs-internal-guid-82322469-d404-a7b1-d295-ee03b476bcfe">Quantitative Reasoning</span></a></h5> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-82322469-d404-cbac-1c7a-d74abefae398">The Quantitative Reasoning requirement is designed to ensure that students graduate with basic understanding and competency in math, statistics, or computer science. The requirement may be satisfied by exam or by taking an approved course.</span></p> <h5><a href="/2019-20/undergraduate/colleges-schools/letters-science/foreign-language-requirement/"><span id="docs-internal-guid-82322469-d404-ff23-6ff3-47abec092456">Foreign Language</span></a></h5> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-82322469-d405-12d9-db19-1b37f6639ef7">The Foreign Language requirement may be satisfied by demonstrating proficiency in reading comprehension, writing, and conversation in a foreign language equivalent to the second semester college level, either by passing an exam or by completing approved course work.</span></p> <h5><a href="/2019-20/undergraduate/colleges-schools/letters-science/reading-composition-requirement/"><span id="docs-internal-guid-82322469-d405-3e15-2491-27223f91e87d">Reading and Composit</span>ion</a></h5> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-82322469-d405-4ef4-4b87-0d26195a0d3c">In order to provide </span>a solid foundation in reading, writing, and critical thinking the College requires two semesters of lower division work in composition in sequence. Students must complete parts A &amp; B reading and composition courses by the end of their second semester and a second-level course by the end of their fourth semester.</p> <h3>College of Letters &amp; Science 7 Course Breadth Requirements</h3> <h5><a href="/2019-20/undergraduate/colleges-schools/letters-science/#breadthrequirementstext"><span id="docs-internal-guid-79a9fe70-d405-7c7e-e34f-837b91cc1d58">Breadth Requirements</span></a></h5> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-82322469-d405-9db4-c30e-bca05ecf44f3">The undergraduate breadth requirements provide Berkeley students with a rich and varied educational experience outside of their major program. As the foundation of a liberal arts education, breadth courses give students a view into the intellectual life of the University while introducing them to a multitude of perspectives and approaches to research and scholarship. Engaging students in new disciplines and with peers from other majors, the breadth experience strengthens interdisciplinary connections and context that prepares Berkeley graduates to understand and solve the complex issues of their day.</span></p> <h3><span id="docs-internal-guid-abca8c8f-d405-c4ad-0be7-1638c654345c">Unit Requirements</span></h3> <ul> 	<li> 	<p>120 total units</p> 	</li> 	<li> 	<p>Of the 120 units, 36 must be upper division units</p> 	</li> 	<li>Of the 36 upper division units, 6 must be taken in courses offered outside your major department</li> </ul> <h5><span id="docs-internal-guid-2bb674c5-d406-43a4-39ed-40d6e86d6760">Residence Requirements</span></h5> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-82322469-d406-8d38-492a-067b2e0bac2d">For units to be considered in &quot;residence,&quot; you must be registered in courses on the Berkeley campus as a student in the College of Letters &amp; Science. Most students automatically fulfill the residence requirement by attending classes here for four years. In general, there is no need to be concerned about this requirement, unless you go abroad for a semester or year or want to take courses at another institution or through UC Extension during your senior year. In these cases, you should make an appointment to meet an adviser to determine how you can meet the Senior Residence Requirement.</span></p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-82322469-d406-a2e5-35d5-82895d287218">Note: Courses taken through UC Extension do not count toward residence.</span></p> <h5><span id="docs-internal-guid-44b2bced-d406-cb13-a0f5-0c6f75ed8972">Senior Residence Requirement</span></h5> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-82322469-d406-e3bd-f620-e9bef1331f97">After you become a senior (with 90 semester units earned toward your BA degree), you must complete at least 24 of the remaining 30 units in residence in at least two semesters. To count as residence, a semester must consist of at least 6 passed units. Intercampus Visitor, EAP, and UC Berkeley-Washington Program (UCDC) units are excluded.</span></p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-82322469-d406-f7f7-c9da-c2732368bc4e">You may use a Berkeley Summer Session to satisfy one semester of the Senior Residence requirement, provided that you successfully complete 6 units of course work in the Summer Session and that you have been enrolled previously in the college.</span></p> <h5><span id="docs-internal-guid-abb18f5b-d407-0e0f-9d41-83c0ea3c3c7b">Modified Senior Residence Requirement</span></h5> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-82322469-d407-3956-aeef-b67b71969fca">Participants in the UC Education Abroad Program (EAP), Berkeley Summer Abroad, or the UC Berkeley Washington Program (UCDC) may meet a Modified Senior Residence requirement by completing 24 (excluding EAP) of their final 60 semester units in residence. At least 12 of these 24 units must be completed after you have completed 90 units.</span></p> <h5><span id="docs-internal-guid-62f287bf-d407-4ca6-5bbd-2d1393418d66">Upper Division Residence Requirement</span></h5> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-82322469-d407-6060-9575-98782777275a">You must complete in residence a minimum of 18 units of upper division courses (excluding UCEAP units), 12 of which must satisfy the requirements for your major.</span></p>
]]>
</collegerequirementstext>
<studentlearninggoalstext>
<![CDATA[
<h3><span style="font-size:1.125em; line-height:21.6px">Learning Goals for the Major</span></h3>
<ol>
	<li>Communicate effectively in a primary foreign language, either Spanish or Portuguese, in written and spoken form.</li>
	<li>Communicate at a basic level in a secondary foreign language, either Spanish or Portuguese.</li>
	<li>Formulate a well-organized, well-supported argument.</li>
	<li>Demonstrate understanding of general research methods.</li>
	<li>Analyze and interpret literary texts.</li>
	<li>Identify major historical figures, events, and trends in Latin America.</li>
	<li>Critically evaluate Latin America’s role and position in a global context.</li>
	<li>Demonstrate awareness and basic knowledge of the multiplicity of countries and cultures that make up the region.</li>
	<li>Apply a minimum of three distinct disciplinary approaches to the study of Latin America.</li>
	<li>Demonstrate specialized knowledge about one or more particular subareas of Latin American studies, whether regional (e.g. the Caribbean; Central America) or topical (agriculture; gender issues; immigration).</li>
	<li>Understand and critically evaluate the implications of different perspectives on Latin America.</li>
</ol>
]]>
</studentlearninggoalstext>
<coursestext>
<![CDATA[
<h3>Latin American Studies</h3>
<div id="sc_sccoursedescs">
<div class="coursedescs_toggleAll notinpdf"><button class="btn_expandAll">Expand all course descriptions [+]</button><button class="btn_collapseAll">Collapse all course descriptions [-]</button></div>
<div class="courseblock">
<button class="btn_toggleCoursebody" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="cb_latamst10" data-toggle="#cb_latamst10">
<h3 class="courseblocktitle">
<span class="code">LATAMST 10</span> 
<span class="title">Introduction to Latin American Studies</span> 
<span class="hours">4 Units</span>
</h3>
</button>
<div class="coursebody" aria-hidden="true" id="cb_latamst10">

<p class="courseblockdesc"><span class="descshow">Terms offered: Fall 2016, Fall 2015, Fall 2014<br/>
This course is intended as a lower division, interdisciplinary core course for students planning to pursue the Latin American Studies major, as well as other interested students. The aim is to provide an introduction to the field that integrates the offerings from the various disciplines. Particular attention will be given to the analysis of the relationship between cultural expression and the politics, economy, and history of the region.</span><br/>
 <a href="" class="btn-readmore"><span>Introduction to Latin American Studies:</span> Read More [+]</a></p>
<div id="271" class="coursedetails" aria-expanded="false">

<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Rules &amp; Requirements</strong></p><p><strong>Repeat rules:</strong> Course may be repeated for credit without restriction.</p></div>
<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Hours &amp; Format</strong></p><p><strong>Fall and/or spring:</strong> 15 weeks - 3 hours of lecture and 1 hour of discussion per week</p><p><strong>Summer:</strong> 8 weeks - 7.5 hours of lecture per week</p><!--<p class=""><strong>Additional Format:</strong> Three hours of Lecture and One hour of Discussion per week for 15 weeks. Seven and one-half hours of Lecture per week for 8 weeks.</p>--></div>
<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Additional Details</strong></p><p><strong>Subject/Course Level:</strong> Latin American Studies/Undergraduate</p><p><strong>Grading/Final exam status:</strong> Letter grade. Final exam required. </p></div>
<p><a href="" class="btn-readless"><span>Introduction to Latin American Studies:</span> Read Less [-] </a></p></div>
</div>
</div><div class="courseblock">
<button class="btn_toggleCoursebody" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="cb_latamst24" data-toggle="#cb_latamst24">
<h3 class="courseblocktitle">
<span class="code">LATAMST 24</span> 
<span class="title">Freshman Seminar</span> 
<span class="hours">1 Unit</span>
</h3>
</button>
<div class="coursebody" aria-hidden="true" id="cb_latamst24">

<p class="courseblockdesc"><span class="descshow">Terms offered: Prior to 2007<br/>
The Freshman Seminar Program has been designed to provide new students with the opportunity to explore an intellectual topic with a faculty member in a small seminar setting. Freshman seminars are offered in all campus departments, and topics vary from department to department and semester to semester. Enrollment is limited to 15 freshmen.</span><br/>
 <a href="" class="btn-readmore"><span>Freshman Seminar:</span> Read More [+]</a></p>
<div id="414" class="coursedetails" aria-expanded="false">

<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Rules &amp; Requirements</strong></p><p><strong>Repeat rules:</strong> Course may be repeated for credit when topic changes.</p></div>
<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Hours &amp; Format</strong></p><p><strong>Fall and/or spring:</strong> 15 weeks - 1 hour of seminar per week</p><p><strong>Summer:</strong> 8 weeks - 2 hours of seminar per week</p><!--<p class=""><strong>Additional Format:</strong> One hour of Seminar per week for 15 weeks. Two hours of Seminar per week for 8 weeks.</p>--></div>
<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Additional Details</strong></p><p><strong>Subject/Course Level:</strong> Latin American Studies/Undergraduate</p><p><strong>Grading/Final exam status:</strong> The grading option will be decided by the instructor when the class is offered. Final exam required. </p></div>
<p><a href="" class="btn-readless"><span>Freshman Seminar:</span> Read Less [-] </a></p></div>
</div>
</div><div class="courseblock">
<button class="btn_toggleCoursebody" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="cb_latamst150" data-toggle="#cb_latamst150">
<h3 class="courseblocktitle">
<span class="code">LATAMST 150</span> 
<span class="title">Advanced Studies in Latin American Studies</span> 
<span class="hours">4 Units</span>
</h3>
</button>
<div class="coursebody" aria-hidden="true" id="cb_latamst150">

<p class="courseblockdesc"><span class="descshow">Terms offered: Fall 2017, Fall 2016, Spring 2016<br/>
Advanced research in current issues or regions of Latin American Studies. The course will focus on specific areas or topics with appropriate comparative material included. Topics change each semester.</span><br/>
 <a href="" class="btn-readmore"><span>Advanced Studies in Latin American Studies:</span> Read More [+]</a></p>
<div id="588" class="coursedetails" aria-expanded="false">

<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Rules &amp; Requirements</strong></p><p><strong>Prerequisites:</strong> Consent of instructor</p><p><strong>Repeat rules:</strong> Course may be repeated for credit without restriction.</p></div>
<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Hours &amp; Format</strong></p><p><strong>Fall and/or spring:</strong> 15 weeks - 3 hours of lecture per week</p><p><strong>Summer:</strong> <br/><span style="width: 15px; display: inline-block;"></span>6 weeks - 7.5 hours of lecture per week<br/><span style="width: 15px; display: inline-block;"></span>8 weeks - 5.5 hours of lecture per week</p><!--<p class=""><strong>Additional Format:</strong> Three hours of Lecture per week for 15 weeks. Five and one-half hours of Lecture per week for 8 weeks. Seven and one-half hours of Lecture per week for 6 weeks.</p>--></div>
<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Additional Details</strong></p><p><strong>Subject/Course Level:</strong> Latin American Studies/Undergraduate</p><p><strong>Grading/Final exam status:</strong> Letter grade. Final exam required. </p></div>
<p><a href="" class="btn-readless"><span>Advanced Studies in Latin American Studies:</span> Read Less [-] </a></p></div>
</div>
</div><div class="courseblock">
<button class="btn_toggleCoursebody" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="cb_latamst160" data-toggle="#cb_latamst160">
<h3 class="courseblocktitle">
<span class="code">LATAMST 160</span> 
<span class="title">The Politics of Development in Chile</span> 
<span class="hours">6 Units</span>
</h3>
</button>
<div class="coursebody" aria-hidden="true" id="cb_latamst160">

<p class="courseblockdesc"><span class="descshow overflow">Terms offered: Summer 2018 First 6 Week Session, Summer 2017 First 6 Week Session<br/>
This course examines the politics of development in Chile. We will consider the different social and economic policies implemented during the years of the Popular Unity Coalition, the Pinochet dictatorship, in the transition back to a democratic political system, and the Concertacion governments that followed. We end the course by studying challenges to the neoliberal model, including the recent massive student</span><span class="deschide"> mobilizations demanding reforms to the educational system, as well as challenges by labor and indigenous groups. We will conclude by considering how globalization shapes the politics of development today.</span><br/>
 <a href="" class="btn-readmore"><span>The Politics of Development in Chile:</span> Read More [+]</a></p>
<div id="736" class="coursedetails" aria-expanded="false">


<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Hours &amp; Format</strong></p><p><strong>Summer:</strong> 6 weeks - 20 hours of lecture per week</p></div>
<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Additional Details</strong></p><p><strong>Subject/Course Level:</strong> Latin American Studies/Undergraduate</p><p><strong>Grading/Final exam status:</strong> Letter grade. Final exam not required. </p></div>
<p><a href="" class="btn-readless"><span>The Politics of Development in Chile:</span> Read Less [-] </a></p></div>
</div>
</div><div class="courseblock">
<button class="btn_toggleCoursebody" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="cb_latamst192" data-toggle="#cb_latamst192">
<h3 class="courseblocktitle">
<span class="code">LATAMST 192</span> 
<span class="title">Senior Thesis</span> 
<span class="hours">3 or 4 Units</span>
</h3>
</button>
<div class="coursebody" aria-hidden="true" id="cb_latamst192">

<p class="courseblockdesc"><span class="descshow">Terms offered: Fall 2008, Spring 2007, Spring 2005<br/>
This course is designed to provide a vehicle for undergraduate students who do not participate in the departmental honors program but are interested in writing a major paper on a Latin American studies topic. The paper should be approximately 30-50 pages in length; the topic must be agreed upon in advance by both the students and faculty sponsor. Requires weekly consultations with faculty sponsor.</span><br/>
 <a href="" class="btn-readmore"><span>Senior Thesis:</span> Read More [+]</a></p>
<div id="714" class="coursedetails" aria-expanded="false">

<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Rules &amp; Requirements</strong></p><p><strong>Prerequisites:</strong> Senior standing</p></div>
<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Hours &amp; Format</strong></p><p><strong>Fall and/or spring:</strong> 15 weeks - 3-4 hours of independent study per week</p><p><strong>Summer:</strong> <br/><span style="width: 15px; display: inline-block;"></span>6 weeks - 3-4 hours of independent study per week<br/><span style="width: 15px; display: inline-block;"></span>8 weeks - 3-4 hours of independent study per week</p><!--<p class=""><strong>Additional Format:</strong> Hours to be arranged. Hours to be arranged.</p>--></div>
<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Additional Details</strong></p><p><strong>Subject/Course Level:</strong> Latin American Studies/Undergraduate</p><p><strong>Grading/Final exam status:</strong> Letter grade. Final exam required. </p></div>
<p><a href="" class="btn-readless"><span>Senior Thesis:</span> Read Less [-] </a></p></div>
</div>
</div><div class="courseblock">
<button class="btn_toggleCoursebody" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="cb_latamsth195" data-toggle="#cb_latamsth195">
<h3 class="courseblocktitle">
<span class="code">LATAMST H195</span> 
<span class="title">Senior Honors Thesis Seminar</span> 
<span class="hours">4 Units</span>
</h3>
</button>
<div class="coursebody" aria-hidden="true" id="cb_latamsth195">

<p class="courseblockdesc"><span class="descshow">Terms offered: Spring 2020, Spring 2019, Spring 2018<br/>
The honors student is required to research and write a thesis based on the prospectus developed in International and Area Studies 102. The thesis work is reviewed by the honors instructor. A second reader is to be selected based on the thesis topic. Weekly reports required.</span><br/>
 <a href="" class="btn-readmore"><span>Senior Honors Thesis Seminar:</span> Read More [+]</a></p>
<div id="626" class="coursedetails" aria-expanded="false">

<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Rules &amp; Requirements</strong></p><p><strong>Prerequisites:</strong> International and Area Studies 102 and consent of instructor; senior standing</p></div>
<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Hours &amp; Format</strong></p><p><strong>Fall and/or spring:</strong> 15 weeks - 3 hours of seminar per week</p><!--<p class=""><strong>Additional Format:</strong> Three hours of Seminar per week for 15 weeks.</p>--></div>
<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Additional Details</strong></p><p><strong>Subject/Course Level:</strong> Latin American Studies/Undergraduate</p><p><strong>Grading/Final exam status:</strong> Letter grade. Final exam not required. </p></div>
<p><a href="" class="btn-readless"><span>Senior Honors Thesis Seminar:</span> Read Less [-] </a></p></div>
</div>
</div><div class="courseblock">
<button class="btn_toggleCoursebody" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="cb_latamst198" data-toggle="#cb_latamst198">
<h3 class="courseblocktitle">
<span class="code">LATAMST 198</span> 
<span class="title">Directed Group Study</span> 
<span class="hours">1 - 4 Units</span>
</h3>
</button>
<div class="coursebody" aria-hidden="true" id="cb_latamst198">

<p class="courseblockdesc"><span class="descshow">Terms offered: Spring 2010, Fall 2009, Fall 2007<br/>
Topics vary from semester to semester.</span><br/>
 <a href="" class="btn-readmore"><span>Directed Group Study:</span> Read More [+]</a></p>
<div id="701" class="coursedetails" aria-expanded="false">

<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Rules &amp; Requirements</strong></p><p><strong>Prerequisites:</strong> Upper division standing and consent of instructor</p><p><strong>Repeat rules:</strong> Course may be repeated for credit without restriction.</p></div>
<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Hours &amp; Format</strong></p><p><strong>Fall and/or spring:</strong> 15 weeks - 1-4 hours of directed group study per week</p><!--<p class=""><strong>Additional Format:</strong> Group meetings to be announced.</p>--></div>
<div class="course-section"><p class="course-heading"><strong>Additional Details</strong></p><p><strong>Subject/Course Level:</strong> Latin American Studies/Undergraduate</p><p><strong>Grading/Final exam status:</strong> Offered for pass/not pass grade only. Final exam not required. </p></div>
<p><a href="" class="btn-readless"><span>Directed Group Study:</span> Read Less [-] </a></p></div>
</div>
</div></div>
]]>
</coursestext>
<faculty>
<![CDATA[
<h2>Faculty and Instructors</h2><h4>Faculty</h4><p class="facitem"><strong>Miguel A. Altieri, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Agriculture, environmental science, pest management.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14371"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Margaret Chowning, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Mexico, history, gender, women, Latin America.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/16790"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Alain De Janvry, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Economics, labor management and policy.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14214"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><h4>Lecturers</h4><p class="facitem"><strong>Stephanie Ballenger, <i>Lecturer</i>. </strong>International and Area Studies.</p><p class="facitem"><strong>Clara I. Nicholls, <i>Lecturer</i>. </strong>International and Area Studies.</p><p class="facitem"><strong>Tiffany L. Page, <i>Lecturer</i>. </strong>                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              .</p>]]>
</faculty>
</courseleaf>

